Well, hello. I'm Derek Radney and I'm a
PCA pastor in Winston-Salem, North
Carolina at Trinity Church. And I'm
hosting this conversation today on
behalf of the Alliance for Mission and
Renewal.
The Alliance exists to help foster a
unified, faithful, and flourishing PCA.
And we're an organization dedicated to
assisting and encouraging churches,
ministry leaders, and all our PCA
sisters and brothers in the work of
communicating the gospel of Jesus Christ
in our current cultural moment.
We celebrate and share stories of the
beautiful ways God is working in and
through our denomination.
My conversation today is with the
Reverend David Richter, who is the
co-director of the Alliance. David has
been a PCA member his whole life. His
father is a teaching elder. He has been
a pastor for 25 years.
And he's been involved in the
denomination on a number of levels,
permanent committees, General Assembly,
presbyteries.
And he's been with the Alliance since
its founding in 20 24. So, David, thank
you so much for joining me.
Yeah, absolutely. It's a It's an honor
to be here.
Well, today I was hoping we could talk
briefly just about the statement that
the AMR board put out in the week of
April 15th or so. And it was sort of
announcing a new chapter for the network
that's been a long time in the making.
And so, I was just hoping you could talk
to us about what's been transpiring over
the past year or so that's led up to
this point.
Yeah, absolutely. I don't think it would
be a surprise to anyone that there has
been a lot about people in our culture
and that is kind of also leaked its way
into the church over the past several
years. I mean, we've seen that kind of
like be manifested in a number of
different ways in the life of our
community and our communion together.
And so, what several leaders from AMR
have done over the past year or so is to
travel around to meet with a number of
different groups around the country and
individuals around the country. And the
main point of that is just been to
listen and try to understand, you know,
what the temperature of the church is,
what the concerns that have existed in
the life of our community are and just
to really try to understand. We didn't
have a pre-packaged kind of agenda to
that. We were really trying to
understand where we were and what some
of those concerns are. And what surfaced
from that is uh
in these conversations was not just a
concern about issues here or there. It
was a kind of a broader concern about
what the tone and the atmosphere and the
trajectory of our common life together
has been. We've been hearing concern
about tightening instincts in the
denomination. Not simply the desire to
uphold our doctrinal standards, but a
tendency to narrow or to borrow a
metaphor that our founding fathers used.
They saw the PCA as kind of a big tent
and with kind of theological markers
that kind of helped us stay within that
tent. That there has been kind of a
tightening of that. Not just with
prudential judgment or pastoral
discretion, but kind of long-standing
breadth that we've enjoyed together.
And anytime that shrinking is kind of
questioning is kind of seen as a a level
of compromise. And we've been hearing
concern about the tone of our discourse
within that, right? Especially online,
but not only online. Many leaders feel
that suspicion and caricature and
rhetorical escalation have become too
normal in our church. Our brothers and
sisters, many feel, have been too
quickly sorted into camps. Motives are
too quickly kind of assigned. And the
ninth commandment has often been honored
in theory rather than practices I talked
about in the article. I've also been
hearing concerns about process. Not
because process doesn't matter. I think
anybody knows me knows that I think
process matters. But because there's a
difference between process that's
serving peace and process that's being
used in ways to deepen distrust and
fear. And
and and that's really important for us
to consider as as a group of people that
have committed themselves to serving the
world together. But that's not all.
We've also heard concerns from our
minority brothers and sisters who
sometimes feel like their experiences
and perspectives or presence in the
denomination can be treated as
politically charged before it's treated
treated as as pastoral. Right? We've had
We've heard concerns from our sisters
and women serving within our
denomination over concern about the
debates that we've been having about
women's roles. Not just, you know, what
side you take on that debate, but also
the tone of it and how it's making our
sisters feel
and the discouragement that it's
bringing across the board in many
different areas in our denomination.
Yeah, for that for that one issue in
particular, that was more before this
year and the deacon question came up
again. It was more about reading
scripture and distributing
element, things like that. More like
participation in worship, right?
Yeah, and we've had a you know, there's
a long history of different strands of
how we've kind of seen that that have
come into our denominational life, but
that has become more heated in the past
few years. And it feels like we're
being, you know, what we some some of
those theological tent markers, right,
are being shrunk within that. And it's
causing reactions on both sides and that
that hasn't, we believe, been healthy.
And there's a lot of concern around that
kind of reality. Um you know, I I think
underneath all of that is what we're
seeing is a larger concern. That the PCA
is slowly becoming more preoccupied with
internal sorting and external than an
external mission. Um more consumed with
controversy than evangelism,
uh church planting and discipleship,
mercy and faithfulness, and our witness
to an age. And And a lot of that has to
do with, you know, disruptive times like
we're living in right now can feel like
we just need to kind of like shrink
inward and focus inward. But
historically in the church, we've seen
those as incredible opportunities for
the gospel to go forward. And when we
can't agree with ourselves and we just
start fighting amongst ourselves, we're
losing, I believe, a wonderful
opportunity to see the gospel go forward
in really powerful ways in the life of
our larger community, our larger
culture.
I was going to ask you why is this
moment in the PCA so important, but I
think in a lot of ways you covered that.
I mean, there's a lot of folks asking
questions about where we're going and
and just sharing concerns about some of
the tone in the conversation. I mean, I
had a lot of people at GA last year come
up to me and just say, "What What's
going on in the PCA? Where are we
going?" You know, and so there does seem
to be a lot of conversation like that.
Yeah, were you going to add to that?
I'm happy to if you want me to. Yeah, go
for it. I mean, if you want to say more
about what what's important about this
moment, that'd be great.
Yeah, I think this moment is important
because denominations are not just
shaped by what they formally confess on
paper, right? They're shaped by what we
reward, what they normalize. If
suspicion becomes normal, if our
rhetoric becomes kind of harsher, like I
believe it has, if our instincts become
increasingly reactive, then even before
formal formality kicks in,
the spiritual climate of the
denomination begins to shift. And that
matters because these are not merely
procedural concerns. They are formative
concerns. They shape the kind of pastors
will flourish. What kind of young
leaders are going to stay in our
denomination and do which leaders are
going to leave. What kind of instincts
elders will bring to their courts and
their congregations. And whether our
people will come to associate
confessional seriousness with things
like wisdom and humility and mission. Or
on the other side of will it be anxiety
and suspicion and kind of endless
internal friction. And I think that
that's why the stakes feel larger right
now and more serious right now. The real
question is what kind of church are we
becoming? We don't believe that the
church needs more torque right now. As I
said in the article, we we believe it
needs more ballast. Not more heat or
reaction. It needs a deeper theological
weight, stronger relational trust, and a
clearer sense of what the PCA is for.
And I think that this is where civility
matters in the kind of these
conversations. You know, Keller Tim
Keller once made the point that civility
is often misunderstood as as niceness or
squeamishness, right? And as if it's a
refusing to contend for truths, but he
went on to say that civility really has
to do with how you how you contend. It's
not a refusal to criticize or but it's a
refusal to caricature, to intimidate,
and to merely marginalize your opponent
rather than actually leaning in and
trying to do the faithful work of what
it means to be
a pastor and a and a denominational
leader or or just a person who's trying
to serve the Lord in faithfulness. Man,
there are great temptations, you know,
to conflict in that way. Our whole
culture is tempted toward conflict in
this way, but some energy in that way is
not the same thing as faithfulness, I
would believe ultimately at the end. So,
this moment matters not only because of
what is being debated, and these are
important things that are being debated,
but because of the kind of church that
we are becoming and how we're debating
those things. And so, just to add on to
that, I think that's a really important
aspect of of what's going on. Yeah.
Yeah.
So, you talked about in your in the
statement that the AMR statement talked
about the need for this confessional
missional center. Yeah. And and about
the need for a a center weight.
Can you talk a little bit more about
that? Just Just say say more for those
who read the article and maybe are still
wanting clarity on what that's about.
Yeah, I mean, in our church, I think
we've kind of began to speak of
ourselves in kind of two different
camps, even confessional or missional.
Even then, we talk about planting
confessional churches or planting
missional churches, right? But when we
speak about this kind of confessional
missional center idea, we are not
talking about a political midpoint
between factions. We're not taking
talking about kind of triangulation or
kind of moderation for moderation's
sake. We are trying to name what we
believe is the one of the really special
historic centers of what our
denomination was intended to be when it
started. Confessional, as we all know,
means kind of being deeply rooted in
scripture as summarized in our doctrinal
standards. It means theological
seriousness and not vagueness in the way
that we approach it. That's incredibly
important why we are who we are in many
ways. Uh and missional and decisive
means outward-facing and evangelistic
and you know, uh fruitful church
planting and discipleship making and you
know, committing to reaching people in
our culture and seeing the gospel quote
go forward with power. And the reason we
believe this kind of center weight is
needed is because denominations do not
stay healthy simply by having strong
edges. Uh they need a strong center. And
we believe that the strong center that
our founding fathers intended was uh for
the church was not to fall off that
horse on one side or the other. And
there's some kind of a there is some
kind of this confessional missional
divide. But they intended to hold these
two things together as they were
intended, I believe by the gospel to be
held together. You cannot have a
faithful confessional side of the church
that is not being pushed out by their
convictions into missional fruitfulness,
right? And uh you cannot have a faithful
missional church that is not solidly
grounded in the confessional and
biblical biblical seriousness that we
believe that our tradition uh has
historically held.
Uh so in this way I
uh these things were meant to be held
together. They're not meant to be
separated. And if we can't hold them
together, uh it will not bode well for
the life of our communion and who we are
as a denomination.
And we get caught up in these kind of
debates around this, you know, account
of weight fights against by force and a
center of weight, you know, is meant to
steady. And so what we mean by that is
that we need this center weight now. And
that's what we mean by ballast as well.
Uh
uh it's not a center weight is not a
voting block. It's not a rival tribe.
It's a kind of a stabilizing
weight rooted in the gospel and that's
strong enough to keep the church from
being pulled off balance uh by fear or
reaction or some kind of factional
energy. Uh
And you know, and a true confessional
missional center should be not marked by
panic or coercive energy. It should be
marked by a theological gravity and a
confidence in the truths that we hold to
uh and enough spiritual steadiness to
contend uh without contempt for one
another. Uh so again, I I I I believe a
center weight is not a faction.
It's a source of theological gravity
that we need to kind of reclaim. And I
believe that our founding fathers in a
really beautiful and special way began
our denomination with that held us
together and saw such fruit and such
beauty over time. Yeah. So the Alliance
is obviously about renewal. It's in the
name, the Alliance for Mission and
Renewal. And that's part of what the
statement uh was about, this kind of
need for renewal
right now. And of course that renewal is
a type of change. You want to see some
sort of change. And there's questions
about what does that mean? What sort of
change does AMR want? Yeah. So maybe you
could talk about that. What is the sort
of change that AMR is hoping to see?
Yeah, absolutely. You know, I think I
would respond by saying that AMR is not
trying to change the PCA's theology or
move the denomination outside of our
historical confessional commitments. Our
burden is not to alter the church's
doctrinal center uh but to strengthen
it. That's our That's really our goal.
Now [clears throat] of course, any
renewal effort or movement, as we hope
we will become, hopes to see change. We
do hope uh for change in tone. We hope
for change in culture. We hope for
change in the way that we contend with
one another. Uh we hope for a greater
trust, uh greater wisdom, and greater
humility, greater theological dialogue.
Uh and that part is important, too. Like
we you know, one of the things that I
think we're losing in all of this is
that we no longer have robust
theological dialogue about a lot of
things anymore. It just gets lost in
camps, right? And we just kind of throw
rocks at each other. You know, we need
to get back to a robust, beautiful
theological dialogue about these
important issues that we're dealing with
so that we can have greater missional
clarity in our denomination. But doing
that is very different than saying that
AMR exists to push the PCA away A away
from its historical center. And you
know, I know that that that is claimed,
but that really truly is not our goal.
Uh in fact, what we're trying to do is
call the PCA toward what we believe is
our best instincts and our best history,
confessional seriousness, pastoral
wisdom, institutional humility,
broad-hearted orthodoxy, and missional
resolve. And in fact, we believe that
that's incredibly important. It's vital.
And you know, one of the things that I
often tell uh people in my my churches
over time, you know, when I'm talking
about the kind of some of these broader
themes is what's the difference between
being faithful and being a jerk to one
another, right? And uh that might sound
silly, but it's not a throwaway line for
where we're at right now. It's actually
kind of a really searching question for
where we're at as a denomination because
one of our great temptations is to
confuse fidelity with harshness in kind
of our dialogue around these things. And
at the same time, we also need to avoid
the opposite mistake. It's wrong to say
peace, peace when there is no peace. Uh
but it is also wrong uh to say fire,
fire when there is no fire. So yes, AMR
is hoping for change. Uh but that change
we're seeking is not a departure from
the PCA's confessional center. It's a
recovery of the kind of theological
ballast and spiritual maturity and
missional health that we believe that is
vital to help the PCA live more
faithfully and fruitfully in the mission
the Lord has called us to in this time
and age.
Yeah, I mean it seems to me that the
articles that AMR published just
recently uh talking about the deacon
issue, it kind of exemplifies what
you're talking about.
Yeah. You know, AMR isn't pushing for
one of those views. In fact, it was
seeking to bring people together with
different views and have a healthy
conversation about that. And so I think
there's there seems to be confusion.
People might think that AMR represents
one of those views uh but really AMR
includes people from sort of the whole
spectrum of the PCA and is trying to
have better conversations. That's just
one area of renewal it seems like AMR's
aimed at. Absolutely. I agree. So the
new AMR vision for the PCA and for AMR
is going to be published very soon. Why
is this needed? Why does AMR have to
come out with a a sort of new vision
statement?
Yeah, you know, the shorter call that
that we put out this past week that I
wrote, it was intended to mark a moment
and kind of like set some of the kind of
the the you know, you know, the markers
by which this conversation can happen.
And this fuller vision statement that
we're going to be putting out over the
next uh few weeks and months uh is is
intended to name the direction of where
we want to go. We felt like a fuller
document or state vision statement was
needed because the season requires more
than just concern.
It requires theological articulation and
institutional clarity. It's not enough
to simply say that what we feel is
unhealthy in our denomination right now.
We also need to say positively what kind
of renewal that we believe the PCA needs
and what kind of denominational culture
we want to strengthen uh and what kind
of theological center we believe needs
to be recovered in our denomination. Uh
in other words, the the vision document
is an effort not only to name anxieties,
but to name hopes. Uh it's trying to not
only say what we are concerned about,
but what we are for. Uh we're trying to
offer not merely critique, but a
constructive theological imagination for
what we're called to be in this world.
And I think that matters because in
moments of tension like we're in right
now, it's always easier to become
reactive than constructive. Um but
renewal requires more than diagnosis. It
requires positive a positive account of
the kind of church that we are called to
become. And that's what we're hoping uh
to do with this statement. Yeah. And it
seems also that like if people want to
get involved, they they need to know
what it is they're kind of signing up to
be a part of. And so just clarifying for
everyone, here's what we're about. And
if you want to help or be a part of
that, here's how you do that. We'll talk
about how people can get involved at the
end. Before I do that, this new vision
is also coming with uh a kind of a a
restructuring of AMR. Um do you want to
talk about the organization itself and
how that's going to be functioning and
what different groups are going to be
doing?
Yeah, and in view of these conversations
that we've been having around the
country, one of the things that we
talked a lot about was, you know, AMR
was originally designed to in the midst
of a really disruptive time where things
had become really negative to try to
highlight a lot of the beautiful and
good things that are happening around
the country right now. Um and that's
really important because there are
incredibly beautiful things that are
happening in the PCA. There's faithful
ministry that's happening. That's, you
know, a mission that's going forward.
Pastors that are preaching the gospel,
women who are serving in really
wonderful ways. And uh that's important
because, you know, I you know, as as I
talk about in the article, uh this idea
of despair, I don't believe is an option
for us as Christians. Uh but neither is
denial. We need to deal with the reality
of the concerns that are happening in
the and these kind of cultural shifts
that are happening and how that's
affecting our life together as
community. And so one of the things that
we talked about in in the wake of these
conversations is that AMR needed to
shift. Uh we needed to kind of lean more
into renewal movement. And with that
needed to come uh a shift in our
structure as an organization and also
kind of some of the things that we were
doing. And so uh we redesigned our
board. We're going to have a couple of
different layers in our board. I'm not
going to get into all the details of
that. We're going to have a large uh
movement board that's going to be made
up of representatives of leaders from
all across the country and from
different perspectives. Uh we're going
to have a board of directors that'll
handle most of our fiduciary kind of
issues. Um and then we're going to have
a steering team that'll have three main
standing teams within it that is really
the heartbeat of the engine of the
mission that we're hoping to kind of
push forward in the next months and
years to come. One of those is a content
content team that's led by a guy named
Shawn Lucas that some of you may have
heard of. Uh Shawn and that team
are going to be working hard on, you
know, putting out thoughtful articles
and engaging theologically with the
different issues that we're engaged with
and also continuing to highlight
beautiful things and beautiful mission
that's going on around our denomination
and around our culture. And the second
team is a kind of a connections team
that's going to be led by David Cassidy.
And And team is going to be designing a
kind of a way forward in relationship to
kind of our need for better
connectivity. Uh there are pastors
around the country that are feeling
isolated. Uh there are pastors that are
feeling uh disconnected from not only
because of the tone of a lot of our
discussions, but because of regional
areas, because of the way these things
are kind of laid out. So, we're going to
be designing a a cohort program uh for
different areas of the country for guys
to come together to be able to engage
with one another. We're also going to be
designing national conference uh at some
point for the same reason, and hopefully
that that's going to help with
connecting guys together, uh leading to
kind of training and development, and
but also kind of shared mission and how
we can learn from each other best
practices, and how we can more
faithfully live out and embody what God
has called us to do in our world. And
then the final piece is a denominational
engagement piece. We
we believe that we need to engage the
denomination in a healthy way, and
that's going to be very public. It's
going to be very out in the open. It's
going to but we are going to uh seek to
to implement some of the things that we
believe need to happen within our
denomination within, you know, uh an
organized way to kind of influence kind
of what's going on uh within our courts.
And, you know, the language we use
around that oftentimes is this idea of
greenhouse. Like, you know, the church
in many ways is like a greenhouse, and
it should be. The greenhouses are are
not the source of life. God is the
source of life, but they they're really
important for creating the environment
that we need in order to do the things
and live out the life that God has
called us to do. And so, you have to
tend to the greenhouse. If there cracks
in the glass or toxins in the soil, we
need to be able to kind of engage with
that in a healthy way that then gives us
the freedom, gives us the power, gives
us that kind of organizational thrust to
be able to go out and to accomplish what
God has called us to.
Backing up a little bit, you had
mentioned the connections team. Are they
going to be doing any regional
gatherings, or is it just a national
gathering and cohorts?
Uh yeah, so the regional gatherings are
the cohorts that I was talking talking
about in in that way. And so, that
absolutely And that's going to be
starting mainly after GA and kind of a,
you know, we're already having
conversations about different ones to
start up, and we're excited about what
that's going to look like. And I should
have said that our denominational
engagement team is going to be led by a
guy named Charles Anderson, uh who's
doing a wonderful job with that right
now.
All right. Well, kind That kind of leads
us to the last thing, which is if people
are interested in this and they want to
follow what's going on, or if they even
want to start getting involved, whether
it's a cohort or the denominational
engagement, how uh how would they do
that?
Well, I would say that the first thing
uh is pretty simple. Uh
stay connected, uh read the statements
that we're putting out, read the vision
documents that are going to be coming
out over the next couple months. You
know, we would encourage you to share
them and discuss them with your elders
and your staff and your friends and to
help people understand what AMR is doing
and how people can get connected in, and
we would really encourage that. And
beyond that, we want people to help
build this kind of center white culture
in places where they are already are. Uh
pastors and elders, deacons, church
planters,
ministry leaders, women serving
faithfully in the church,
may people who are deeply uh committed
to the kind of the long-term health of
the PCA. So, we would encourage that. Um
if you're interested in, you know, uh
cohorts or connections or writing or
getting involved more with
denominational health, you know, I've
kind of outlined a little bit of, you
know, the structure that we have, so I
would encourage you to reach out and and
and try to get engaged with that.
You know, uh and that's really
important. Renewal is not built by
spectators.
And, you know, I think one of the things
that we're encouraging is that I we know
that, you know, involvement sometimes is
not sexy, right? Uh engagement is not
sexy, but it's important and we take
vows
for the health of our denomination. So,
we're encouraging people to get involved
and get connected in in these different
ways so we can help and serve our
community.
You know, and I would add that part of
getting involved is not only
organizational, it's spiritual and
pastoral. One of the strongest themes
uh in uh this kind of idea of how we
should be civil with one another is uh a
warning against tribalism, uh the
tendency to see sin as something out
there rather than in our own hearts, and
that's really important. If this is
going to be a work of renewal, it cannot
simply be about gathering people who are
frustrated with other people. It has to
be involved repentance and faith and
humility and a recovery of gospel-rooted
love for the church. So, getting
involved means more than just joining a
network.
It means helping embody a different way
of being the PCA, truthful being without
being shrill, courageous without being
quarrelsome, confessional without being
sectarian, missionally alive without
being doctrinally thin, right? So, I
think that that's vitally important, and
that's the kind of culture that we're
hoping to build.
Well, in some ways it seems like this is
Some people might balk at this, but it's
sort of um a conservative movement. I
mean, there's a let's let's maintain
the the culture and the mission and the
doctrine of the PCA that that was there
at the founding, and we just need to
tend to our health and try to try to
preserve that and promote that. Yeah,
absolutely. Yeah, absolutely. All right.
Well, David, thanks so much for taking
time to uh talk a little bit with me and
to just articulate a a little bit more
about what AMR is doing and how we've
kind of gotten to this point. If you're
watching still, thank you for uh
listening in, and we just ask for for
patience as we try to enroll some of
this vision, and we do want to be very
up front and clear about what AMR is all
about, and we we do think questions are
going to be answered in due time. So,
stay tuned, and thank you for listening.